all right
hello everyone welcome to actin flab
guest stream number 16.1
with mark solms it's january 22nd 2022.
it's gonna be an awesome discussion we
really appreciate everyone taking the
time out to participate in the live
stream and in the discussion
we're going to have some intermittent
presentation intervals by professor
solms and uh also a period for
discussion
alternating with that so we'll each just
introduce ourselves and then pass it
directly to the presentation section so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i'll pass to dave
i'm dave i'm a software developer and
student of psychology i live 200
kilometers north of manila
hello i'm stephen i'm based in toronto
canada
and i'm doing a practice-based phd
around
social topographies and how people
engage in community development and
i'll pass it over to mark now welcome
thanks very much
so what i propose to do is to
in a moment i'll share my screen and
you'll see my slides
um i'm going to start with the summary
slide of all the points that
i
propose to cover
and then i'll take them one by one each
of those points
and
at the end of each of them i'll stop and
see if anyone wants to comment or ask a
question and then we slowly plow through
it like that we've got two hours
so
it should be okay but if worse comes to
worst and we don't get to the end of the
list of topics
we will arrange a follow-up meeting to
to conclude to conclude them
so i'm very glad to be here thanks for
inviting me and i'm really looking
forward to this discussion
here come my slides
um
on the screen is the title of my book
and here is the promised summary of what
i'm going to cover
as i said uh i'll i'll cover each of
these points in turn
and uh if we don't and then we'll have
questions and comments
in between
and if we don't get to the end that's
fine let's rather let's rather give each
one of the topics the time that it needs
so i start with the
with the um
assertion
that affect is the foundational form of
consciousness
and that affect is intrinsically
conscious
i then move to
make the point that that claim that
affect is intrinsically conscious in
other words that you can't have a
feeling that you don't feel
that this is not based on semantic
arguments but rather on empirical
evidence
and i will summarize the evidence
i'll then make
the point that affect is not synonymous
with interceptive inference which is
widely believed these days
and i'll tell you why that matters when
i get there
and then i'll move on to
making the point that all of this casts
new light on the hard problem
particularly if affect is not just an
intraceptive form of perception because
there are lots of problems
about perception
that
have got us into this heart problem in
the first place
i'll argue that affect rather than being
intraceptive inference that it's an
extended form of homeostasis
i'll tell you what that what i mean by
that when we get there and i'll make the
point that complex organisms like
ourselves require multiple homeostats
and that these are to be treated as
categorical variables which matters
and that these variables must be
prioritized one can't meet all one's
needs simultaneously
i'll then uh this is an a large point
this one is a large point the the the
empirical evidence about affect and this
one is another large point the mechanism
of perceptual and cognitive
consciousness is precision modulation of
allostatic prediction errors
that's a big claim and so we must spend
some time on it
i'll then
talk about the nature of the predictive
hierarchy i seem to see it a little
differently from most people so i want
to set out my stall on that score
and explain why i think the predictive
hierarchy is arranged concentrically
and that this
with
as one moves toward the periphery of the
hierarchy
there's progressively increasing
tolerance of uncertainty
and then lastly
i'll say a word or two about why i think
that consciousness can be artificially
engineered
so even if we don't get to the end of
all of these topics one way or another
even if we're the second meeting those
are the topics we will cover
and we'll see how far we get tonight and
at least you know what the over what the
overall when i say tonight i'm in berlin
i know it's morning for some of you
but at least you get the overall picture
from that slide so let's start with
affect is the foundational form of
consciousness and it's intrinsically
conscious
uh the discoverer
of the unconscious i quote him uh
because freud more than anybody wanted
us to
realize just how much of mental life is
unconscious
even freud said that it is surely of the
essence of an emotion that we should be
aware of it
that is that it should become known to
consciousness
thus the possibility of the attribute of
unconsciousness would be completely
excluded
as far as emotions feelings and affects
are concerned it's quite a startling
statement
from as i said the discoverer of the
unconscious to say that the possibility
of the attribute of unconsciousness
would be completely excluded as far as
emotions feelings and affects are
concerned
now i know this is a controversial
issue
and that there are all sorts of ways in
which people want to argue that there
are such things as unconscious emotions
and what not
um and this has partly to do with the
fact that different people mean
different things by these words
uh emotions affects and so on
um and it has
there are also all kinds of
methodological um
operationalizations of these things
uh i won't go into all of that i'm happy
to if any of you want to discuss it but
i've i've emphasized the word feelings
to make clear that
um
if anyone wants to argue that
they think that the word emotion
can apply to unconscious processes or
affects can apply to unconscious
processes
that's fine by me
but the word feelings i don't see how
you can ever argue that feelings can be
unconscious
it just doesn't make any sense that a
feeling
could exist without being felt if it
were not felt it would not be a feeling
and so i'm going to focus
everything that i'm going to say on this
process this this thing
this this mental state
called feelings
and i'm arguing that feelings
are the foundational form of
consciousness and that these this form
of consciousness is intrinsically
conscious
um
so
that's as a sort of a dogmatic statement
i'm not sure if anyone wants to discuss
that
perhaps you want to hold your horses
but that's the end of my first
point
so anyone who wants to interrupt here
go ahead otherwise i'll move on
thanks for the
digestible claim-based format my
question would be what else has been
posited in your view
as a foundational form of consciousness
so what are the counter factuals for
that first claim what other horses are
in the race
um
the
reason i focus on effort um well i
shouldn't say the reason i focus on
effort because that's not quite what
you're asking you're asking what are the
other horses in the race so let me say
that the whole
search for a neural correlate of
consciousness which is in a way where
the trouble began
um
with with francis crick
it was focused on visual perception
and they're good reasons to focus on
visual perception
uh
mainly because if you
take a look at your you'll excuse the
pun take a look at your consciousness
right now
it's probably dominated by visual
perception uh visual qualia predominates
in our consciousness
and
a very large part of our cortex is given
over to visual processing
and
everybody's always believed that cortex
is where it's at when it comes to
consciousness and
we also understand a very great deal
about
visual cortical mechanisms and visual
mechanisms all together so that was a
perfectly reasonable place to start so
that's the other main horse that's in
the race but vision was thought to be a
good model example not because it is the
totality of consciousness but because it
was assumed that if we can crack the
problem of how visual consciousness
arises then we can generalize our
conclusions to other forms
and i'm going to argue that there's
something
profoundly different about visual
consciousness and affect of
consciousness
and moreover
that there's something profoundly
different about
cortical consciousness
and the brain stem mechanisms which
is
where affect of consciousness arises and
i know that i'm saying that
boldly now and i'm about to argue that
point uh
in the second of the of the bullet
points uh on the screen uh affect of
consciousness is not a cortical form of
consciousness it's a brainstem form and
that the cortical form of consciousness
is contingent upon the brain stem form
and
this is this is one of the main reasons
apart from evolutionary reasons which
sort of interdigitate with and flow from
that from that anatomical localization
um why i think that affect is the
foundational form so it's really vision
that i'm using as my account my kind of
foil
to answer the question simply
stephen
one question with feelings is
would you say that feelings are
integrated with proprioception in the
sense that they um are felt sense
of where the body is as well so it
brings it into kind of an
action-orientated domain
or
is it enough to have um
sort of a sense of how things are going
sort of an overview of just an emotional
state
and and then whether those two
connecting some way
um
as i'm going to argue when i get to my
third point
i don't think that affect is synonymous
with intraceptive inference altogether
interceptive perception altogether um
and i don't know some people would
would class proprioception with
interreception uh some people would not
some people would say it's a sort of a
it's a sort of a hybrid
between intercepted and extraceptive
perception
but to the extent that by the word
proprioception you're referring to a
form of perception
i would disagree with that because i
don't think that affect is a form of
perception i think that proprioception
follows um
if if by proprioception you mean what
what neurologists normally mean by that
word it's it's a it's it's part of the
broader category of somatic sensation
um
and
therefore uh uh that does not uh qualify
uh i think as affective
um
because as i say i'm going to argue that
affect is not a form of perception
there there
i draw a distinction uh as do you know i
think it's it's perfectly uh um
fine to draw a distinction between
extraceptive bodily sensations and
interceptive bodily sensations but i
think that the interceptive type
is is is nothing other than perception
and not intrinsically different
so even if you think of proprioception
as straddling those two domains i still
think that it's a modality of perception
and suffers from all the same problems
as vision for that reason
i see we have a comment in the chat line
i'm not sure how how we're going to deal
with that if one of yous
i'll read this it was a question in the
live chat from ingrid they wrote
what differentiates affect from feeling
from your perspective
is affect conscious or pre-conscious
thank you
um you know
this is uh
a perennial problem
we don't all mean the same thing by
these terms
so that's why
i've focused on the word feeling because
there can be little doubt what feeling
denotes it denotes something you feel in
other words something that you are
necessarily aware of
if you were not aware of it you it
wouldn't be called a feeling because you
wouldn't feel it
um
affects and emotions denote many
different things to different people
so
when you ask me is affect pre-conscious
or conscious and so on it depends what
you mean by affect um to my mind and i
can only say um you know
just make clear how i use these words uh
i use the word feeling
to denote the subjective experience of
affect uh affect is a kind of abstract
term for a function
that we feel um but that doesn't mean
that you all have to use the word in the
same way and it's precisely in order to
not get lost in this kind of semantic
tangle uh that i'm focusing on the word
feeling
and i'll make clear
in the very point that i'm moving to
next uh what i mean by feeling in terms
of its um
it's it's physiological and anatomical
and other objective
um
instantiations
excellent stephen you you have your hand
up
probably just didn't oh is that your
previous hand
so just
go to the second point okay
very good so the second point is
as you saw we've just been talking about
the meaning of the words
um and i've i've um staked my claim
for the word feeling
to make clear that that's what i mean
when i say that affect is intrinsically
conscious i mean that it is necessarily
felt
um i'm also saying it's the foundational
form of consciousness that doesn't flow
from the word
except perhaps from the word in the
sense that the way that nagel and
chalmers
define consciousness and many people
seem to have sort of
agreed with this way of defining it that
there is something it is like to be
conscious that that this something it is
likeness
it
seems to be more or less the same thing
as feeling it seems to mean the same
thing but feeling in a rather broader
sense of the word than affective feeling
so i want to be clear now
why other than those other than those
linguistic or semantic points
why i'm making this claim
about feeling it's not by any means
based in the semantics that you have to
feel a feeling i i want to be clear
why i think
that this is the foundational form of
consciousness
we've we've all known since
when there was this big surprise that
magoon and mirzi found
that all consciousness is contingent
upon what we subsequently called
reticular activating arousal in other
words upon the something that's
contributed by
these core brain stem structures
which after magoon and maritz's work
came to be known as the reticular
activating system
i want to be clear i'm
not only talking about the reticular
activating system but also about the
periaqueductal gray which is not
technically part of the reticular
activating system but it is part of
the brain structures
which seem to be fundamental
to the generating of consciousness
um the what magoon and marutzi showed
among other things what was that if you
make a small lesion above the reticular
activating system thereby severing it
disconnecting it from the forebrain and
from the cortex
in particular
then consciousness
is obliterated entirely
consciousness is 100
dependent upon brain stem arousal
that was a shock
and a shock that i don't think
we have fully come to terms with even
all these years later
it should have led us to realize that
we've been looking in the wrong place uh
for
the neural correlate of consciousness if
we're looking to cortex because it's
plain even from just that study
performed in 1948
that cortical consciousness
is derived from elsewhere cortical
conscious consciousness cannot
occur
in the absence of reticular
arousal
but
the way that magoon and maruzi
fudged it was to say
and everyone more or less
in their wake has said the same
that it turns out they're two kinds of
consciousness
there's the brainstem kind uh which we
call wakefulness
or the level of consciousness
um and then there's the cortical kind
which we call awareness
or the phenomenal um
contents of consciousness
so this distinction between a
quantitative level contributed by the
brain stem and qualitative contents
contributed by the cortex
is
the way in which we save the cortical
theory of consciousness
following magoon and lewis's
seminal observations in case you're
wondering what this refers to uh it
refers to a more recent study by fisher
and colleagues which showed that the
smallest lesion necessary to produce
coma in human beings is a two cubic
millimeter
lesion in other words a lesion the size
of a match head
in the parabrachial complex
so there's no doubt on the basis of
magoon and meruzi studies all those
years ago and on the basis of these
much more recent observations
that
that consciousness cannot exist without
whatever it is that this part of the
brain contributes this this primitive
brainstem call
but this
idea that it's merely a
a level or a or a quantitative dimension
of consciousness is what
i i think is unsustainable
and i'm going to very quickly because
i'm sure many of you have heard me
talking about this before i going to
very quickly whiz through the evidence
for why
this this
notion that the brain stem contributes
only a quantitative level a sort of a
wakeful prerequisite uh for
consciousness uh rather than
equality and the content
um but i want to before i do that to
just give you a clear picture
of what is meant by this distinction um
the the the distinction uh is is is
analogous to
uh the difference between a television
set and its power supply
uh the idea that the cortex is
responsible for the contents and
qualities of consciousness for
phenomenal consciousness the real stuff
the real failure of consciousness where
the
the thing that all the arguments are
about
um it's that this is like the television
set
and it has to be plugged in
uh of course you can't a television set
can't do its television thing
unless it's powered up uh
but
to claim therefore that the real source
of television and and all that that word
represents uh is the power supply the
electrical uh source uh in the wall uh
is ludicrous
and and that's pretty much how we've all
seen until very recently how we've all
seen what the brain stem contributes to
consciousness so nobody's doubting that
it's necessary that it's prerequisite uh
that that without it you can't have
cortical consciousness but it's been
it's been uh
reduced to a mere power supply something
which is not actually consciousness
itself in the sense that that we're all
arguing
about
so why do i think that that's not
correct
well uh
i'll start with the most dramatic
evidence which is patients who have no
cortex
if the theory that the cortex is
necessary for the contents and qualities
of consciousness
then
patients without cortex should be in a
coma
or at the very least if we claim that
the brain stem produces nothing other
than the sort of background level
then
patients with no cortex should have some
kind of blank wakefulness
i suppose the closest uh
natural
kind of thing
that tallies with blank wakefulness
is the
vegetative state
which is also called non-responsive
wakefulness in other words there's
wakefulness without anybody being there
without it there being anything it is
like
for
the
organism that has blank wakefulness uh
due to the absence of cortex but when
you look
at cases who who have no cortex and
here's the scan of a girl
with hydrant encephali born with no
cortex
and you
examine the girl herself you see that
she's not only conscious in other words
not in a coma she's conscious in the
sense that she wakes up in the morning
goes to sleep at night
but more interestingly
she is responsive remember my definition
or the definition
of the vegetative state
the state of blank wakefulness
it is non-responsive wakefulness and
clearly this girl is not non-responsive
here she's responding
to
the placement of her baby brother on her
lap and she responds emotionally in a
way that any kid
any little girl
place a baby on her lap she'll she'll
she'll
most will express pleasure most most
kids like their little baby siblings
being placed on their laps
um and it's not just her it's most of
these kids
if they're if they're raised in
something other than a state of complete
deprivation
like romanian orphans
who fall into what might look like a
vegetative state
although their cortex is entirely intact
if you actually raise these kids in
in reasonably humane conditions
they are conscious and responsive uh
affectively responsive that's the main
point that they're making these children
with absolutely no
no cortex their consciousness has a
quality and the content
that quality we call affect
it feels like something to be these kids
and the content
is not monotonous affect it's all kinds
of effort that he has a summary slide
for extracting
what beyond marco who studied many many
many of these kids what he said about
them they show all of these different
emotions
and most importantly of all they show
them in situationally appropriate ways
in other words they respond with
laughter if they're tickled uh they
respond uh with with arched backs and
and and and and protests uh if something
that they want uh is denied them uh they
respond with a startle uh if there's a
sudden uh unexpected noise and so on
so
uh the evidence is that these kids are
not only conscious in the sense of being
awake
which is interesting in itself in fact i
can't imagine what a state of blank
wakefulness might be like but there you
have it the
the the the the concept uh derived from
lagoon and naruto's work is that there
is such a theoretical fiction as blank
wakefulness but these kids are not black
uh these kids are emotionally responsive
in exactly the way that you would expect
if they had consciousness at least in
the form of affect
so i'm arguing that
with no cortex at all
these kids
display the content and qualitative
conscious contents and qualities
in the form of affects
now of course the big methodological
problem is that how do you know what
it's like to be these kids how do you
know if there's anything it's like to be
these kids they can't tell us anything
about what it's like to be them
so uh all you can do um
in this situation
is is look at other lines of evidence
if we can find multiple converging lines
of evidence converging on the conclusion
that the brain stem is where the affects
are actually generated
then
we can do no better we can do no more we
can do nothing other than that in
science so i want to show you now uh
what happens if we look at cases you can
speak who've lost
great swathes of cortex
we
they can't have lost all of their cortex
because otherwise they wouldn't be able
to speak to us so i'm wanting to show
you examples of cases who have lost
great swathes of cortex and the cortex
in question is the cortex that has been
that that has been most closely
identified uh with
with with sentient being with with the
subjective
presence
of a mind of a conscious mind
the first
example is of prefrontal cortex
i think that it's fair to say that the
mainstream view is that where all of
this information processing comes
together and is
received by a sentient subject of the
mind the mainstream view is that
would be in the prefrontal cortex
now there are few patients there it's
rare to have a patient with absolutely
no prefrontal cortex but here's one
example and i'm just giving you examples
in in this presentation i'm speaking
about individual cases those individual
hadron and cephalic kids that you just
saw um they are representative
of the class of patient that i'm talking
about here is a patient of my own um who
has no prefrontal cortex but happily uh
has a sliver of language cortex and so
he's able to tell us what it's like to
be him i asked him if he was conscious
of his thoughts and he said yes of
course i am and i explained to him that
according to classical theory he
shouldn't be
so
in order to confirm that he's conscious
of his thoughts i asked him if uh if he
would be willing to solve a problem that
would require him to consciously picture
a situation in his mind and he agreed to
do that so i said
the i want him to picture in his mind i
want him to imagine
that he has two dogs and one chicken
which is which he then says okay he'll
do and then i ask him do you see them in
your mind's eye and he says yes he does
i then ask him to count the legs you
know this is not an everyday task it's
something that's unexpected so there he
has these two dogs in his mind's eye and
a chicken and he has to count the legs
and of course the answer is 10.
i ask him how many legs do you see and
he says to my great disappointment he
says eight
i say eight and he says yes the dog's at
the chicken
uh which um i think is uh enough
evidence for me that this chap uh is
there you know that there's there's
there's somebody at home uh who's
looking at these
dogs and the chicken
and imagining perhaps concretely you
know that the dog's actually at the
chicken
or perhaps
he's pulling a fast one he's making it a
joke
and in fact the making of pure oil jokes
is a very common feature
of patients with the frontal lobe
syndrome
and this is linked traditionally with
the commonplace observation that these
patients are
emotionally disinhibited
and why i draw your attention to that is
that if it were true that the cortex and
the prefrontal cortex in particular is
where affects are generated then how
come
if you have an absence of prefrontal
cortex not only is affect preserved but
affect is excessive uh there's
there's more effect than normal there's
there's too much effect
this is
entirely
incompatible with the idea
espoused by many
respectable neuroscientists
joseph ledoux for example who's a
great authority
on affect
joseph ledoux says that of course the
amygdala and other subcortical machinery
for anxiety doesn't actually generate
any feeling at all that the feeling of
anxiety is read out to use his term
labeled by the prefrontal cortex and
that's when it actually turns into a
conscious experience
so i say again if that were true then
how come
not only my patient this one making this
joke to us uh but all frontal lobe
patients
the the less frontal cortex they have
the more affect they have
so the less capacity they have to read
out and label their feelings somehow it
seems as if they're beset by more
feeling rather than less
um since i'm talking about feelings
the other major candidate
the other major cortical candidate
as being the seat of the sentient self
is the insula
bud craig claims that the insular or
perhaps even just the anterior third of
it is where the sentient subject comes
into being and he links this
particularly with affect he says that
this is the part of the cortex
which registers
the state of the own body
how do you feel now
is registered by
this part of the cortex
and it's on this basis that he claims
that this is where the sentient subject
comes
into being
so again
in just one case like marzia who had
absolutely no insulin bilaterally
obliterated and he interviewed in much
the same way
as i interviewed my patient with no
frontal cortex
and demarzio asks him if he has a sense
of self and he says yes he does and i
won't go through all of this all of
which is
dimarzio trying to
ascertain whether or not this person
is conscious and in particular whether
or not he possesses selfhood does he
even understand what self food is
and eventually demarzia says what if i
were to tell you that i know you better
than you know yourself patience says i
would think you're wrong
demarzia says what if i were to tell you
that you're aware that i am aware
patient says i'd say you're right the
marzia says you're aware that i'm aware
patient says i am aware that you're
aware that i'm aware please note all
these references to i
uh there is a sentient subject speaking
to us here
with absolutely no
insular cortex
so i think the claim on the basis of
the hydrant and cephalic children
the claim that the cortex is the seat of
consciousness and of feeling in
particular
has to be dismissed uh but they can't
speak so we look at the other major
candidates who can speak patients with
no prefrontal cortex they are conscious
there's a sentient subject there and
they feel like something they tell us
and they show us
and likewise patients with no insulin
cortex
of course the claim can be made well in
these cases
their consciousness arises from the
remnants of the cortex the remainder of
the cortex the quarter the cortex that
is not removed bear in mind the ones who
have no cortex you know who clearly show
behavioral displays of affect
every prediction that you might make
from the hypothesis that it feels like
something to be these kids is confirmed
by their behavior
by their responses to affective stimuli
and
in that case we say well we don't know
because they can't speak
so then we use these other cases with no
prefrontal cortex no insular cortex who
can speak and then we say well it must
be the the other bits of the cortex that
are generating the consciousness it
seems like a
losing wicket to me
but
let's look at other evidence then lesion
evidence
remember we're looking for converging
lines of evidence converging on the
conclusion that the feelings are
generated in the brainstem
in the brainstem
and so here we look at the case
of a patient in where an entirely
different method is used that is deep
brain stimulation of a part of the
reticular activating system in this case
the substantia
the surgeon was aiming for the
subthalamic nucleus but the
the electrode went into the substantia
and when he stimulated it the
patient fell into a profound depression
within five seconds again i'm not going
to read all of this to you it'll it
will take more time
than is necessary
if you read it yourself
you'll see this patient within five
seconds felt fell into a profound
depression
as she has no psychiatric history never
been depressed before never had a
diagnosis of any kind led to learn a
diagnosis of major depression and here
within five seconds you can generate
produce cause
a suicidal depressive state
which within 30 seconds of switching off
uh the
uh the the stimulator 90 seconds i mean
after the stimulation will stop the
depression stops
very interestingly
she
agreed or very bravely she agreed to
have the stimulator
switched on and off
either in the subthalamic nucleus or in
the substantia of the reticular
activating system where she was blind as
to where the stimulation was being
applied and every time it was applied in
the reticular activating system she fell
into this severe depressive state again
so this is you know this is what you
would expect this is the the prediction
uh from the hypothesis that ethics are
actually generated in the brain stem
the the the prediction would be if you
stimulate these reticular activating
nuclei you will generate affects and
that's exactly what you do
this is also why i mentioned the
periaqueductal gray earlier
because
if you stimulate reticular activating
nutri you generate intense effects but
the same applies to periaqueductal gray
in fact the greatest intensity and range
of affects anywhere in the brain can be
elicited from deep brain stimulation of
the periaqueductal brain
brain stimulation of the cortical mantle
produces very little if any affect
um another method positron emission
tomography so another study of
demarzio's patients in states of anger
sadness happiness and fear uh you see
where the brain
the
the major brain activity is in all of
these affective states the major
activities subcortical it's in the brain
stem it's not cortical
so again this is exactly what you would
predict if the affect is actually being
generated by the brain stem not being
read out by the cortex but generated by
the brain stem
and then there's also the matter of the
neurotransmitters that
psychopharmacologists tinker with
the mainstream psychiatric medications
modulate
neurotransmitters that are sourced in
the reticular activating system
we don't normally think of it that way
but it is
simply the case
that serotonin which we increase
with antidepressants
is sourced in the reticular activating
system dopamine which we block with
antipsychotics
is sourced in the reticular activating
system noradrenaline
which
is blocked in
many anti-anxiety drugs
is sourced in the reticular activating
system if the reticular activating
system was just the power source
uh that i referred to in my analogy
about the television set then it should
only interest anesthetists
you shouldn't be able to change the
channel
alter the programming of the television
set by pulling out the plug or by
or by attenuating the power supply you
might expect the screen to sort of go
blank or or just flicker but not to have
whole new programs with new contents and
new qualities
and so this is my argument that the the
idea that feeling states affective
feeling states of the kind that those
children display
of the kind that these patients describe
of the kind that psychiatrists are
or directly trying to manipulate
are generated by upper brain stem
structures they're not generated by
cortex you don't need to have cortex in
order to have these states and yet
we all know and agree we all agree that
cortical consciousness is contingent
upon reticular activating arousal
if we now
are forced to accept that reticular
activating arousal is not contentless is
not a mere quantity it's not just a
level
but rather has content and quality that
we call affect then we have to accept
that affect is a prerequisite for all
other forms of consciousness and it's on
this basis not on semantic one that i'm
claiming that affect is the foundational
form of consciousness uh it also makes
good evolutionary sense uh that this
ancient structure
rather than the cortical mantle which
evolves only with mammals
that the ability to register your own
subjective state how you're doing
effectively in terms of hunger and
thirst and sleepiness
and to hotness and whatnot
that this should not require
such a late evolutionary development but
that's another point i'm just wanting to
slot in there that i also mean it in the
evolutionary sense when i say that
affect is the foundational form of
consciousness i don't only mean it in
the functional sense
now i'll pause there because that's a
big claim
and a very controversial claim
in fact i must tell you i'm still
slightly
dismayed that it remains controversial
i've been i've been really surprised by
the degree of pushback that i get
when i argue and it's i'm not the only
one who argues that i'm not the first
one to argue it
but
demarzia argues that
panxip was the first to argue it
marker argues it
and
here i come a good few years on and
argue the same thing citing all of this
evidence and uh
wow people just don't want to accept it
so let's hear what what
what you have to say
stephen
yeah yeah i'll read a question from the
chat first and then we'll go to stephen
so
uh jonathan in the in the chat wrote
i can imagine a modern large language
model the likes of gpt3 creating such
conversations without apparently having
a mind's eye
while i agree it is good evidence i
think we are seeing machine learning
systems having similar conversations so
you've presented case studies that are
the tip of the iceberg of broader
populations and analyses how do we think
about
our evaluation of conversational
dialogue
in
questions about necessity and
sufficiency here
yeah you see this is a kind of a
um a relative of the philosophical
zombie uh argument
uh the the problem is with this sort of
thing is that
in fact the same applies uh to you and
me
i can't know for sure that daniel is
conscious that stephen is conscious that
david is conscious
or that the person who asked that
question is conscious you know
the point you've just made really does
apply in exactly the same way there's no
greater reason to believe that it
applies to the patients that i've just
presented to you then and that it
applies to you and me
because you too could be a philosophical
zombie in other words you too could look
as if and you have internal states say
that you have internal states but
actually there's nobody there i can
never
disprove that
that is a metaphysical
problem that's not a scientific problem
the scientific method is requires
that your hypothesis has to be
consistent with all the known facts um
and then you have to make falsifiable
predictions
from that hypothesis
and if your predictions are not
falsified then they are upheld
unless uh and until uh they some
evidence is found which positively this
is what positivism is all about which
positively falsifies it so i'm saying
these kids look as if they're conscious
you know
they behave as if they're conscious now
it's true that they might not be and
stephen might not be and daniel might
not be and david might not be but you
know
my hypothesis is that they are so what
do i do i say well if daniel
feels pain like i do then when i stick a
pin uh in his hand he's going to go ouch
and withdraw his hand and avoid me in
future
and that's uh you know that's a
confirmation of my prediction uh the
same applies for these kids
but you know that's just one source of
evidence as i said you don't accept just
one
you then say okay well what about this
line of evidence what about that and
i've given you five lines of evidence
here
in which in every instance uh the
prediction from the hypothesis
that these people are conscious and that
the consciousness is generated in the
brain stem and that that it has an
affect of quality every single line of
evidence
you know the prediction is confirmed
what you would expect would happen if
that were true is what happens
so
you know
i'm afraid you can do no more than that
in science um and it's a curious fact
that we raise the bar uh of evidence uh
when it comes to the problem of
consciousness um i think we must be very
careful not to require um any different
sort of evidence in the case of
consciousness then we require for any
other
matter in science
and in this case in any other
biological function you know it's
if you start with the assumption that
consciousness is something special
that you know the ordinary rules of
science don't apply to then you're going
to have a self-fulfilling prophecy
so yes it's possible it's possible that
these kids and those patients are not
there that they're lying to me uh that
you know
it's it's a little bit of a curious
thing that somebody without a sense of
self uh wants to pretend that they've
got one um i think you're in a kind of
slippery slope there to to uh
to
to irrationality
but
i can't prevent you from holding that
view it's just not consistent with any
of the evidence i'm afraid
thank you mark stephen
yeah i was wondering how much you think
the challenge with uptake is because
people are sort of stuck in
the idea that
knowledge and information is a signal
coming in
and
meaning it's all about meaning and the
ability to communicate meaning
as opposed to
engaging in meaningful action and
skillful
inactive processes of the voice
twitching
the voice box twitching and enabling
words to be in the space around us
in some sort of way and whether that
that issue is um kind of a deeper
ingrained
challenge to overcome
well i completely agree with that i
think that that is the
the
a fundamental source of the problem
um
because our common sense tells us our
consciousness is extraceptive as i said
earlier you know the
our conscious experience is dominated by
visual qualia and where do they come
from from you know
things light waves impinging on my
retina from outside and i'm seeing
things out there and so consciousness
seems
to be
so obviously derived from something out
there
um and this is
this was at the heart of the experiments
that magoon and maruzi did
magoon and maruzi weren't expecting to
find what they found
um that they were expecting that
a cat deprived of any extraceptive
stimuli will fall asleep um if not fall
into a coma
and it was therefore a great surprise to
find that that's not what happens
that the consciousness is generated
endogenously comes from deep within the
brain doesn't flow in with sensory
stimuli
um and
when they lesion that core brain stem
structure the lights went out
and
they couldn't make sense of it and they
came up with this
with this uh theory which as i've shown
you at least as i've shown to anyone
who's you know who's willing to look at
the evidence and draw the conclusions uh
that uh
this that the the way that they framed
it is wrong it doesn't explain
what they saw what they saw was that
consciousness is endogenously generated
and where does that where does the
notion come from this common sense
notion
that it flows in from outside it comes
not only from our own
everyday experience but also from the
british empiricist philosophers who
probably themselves derived it from
common sense you know that
the mind literally the mind as a whole
you know is is derived from sensory
experience
that leaves impressions uh
leaves memory images impressed upon our
cortex which are then associated with
each other and this according to british
empiricist philosophy which underpinned
the whole of 19th century
and early 20th century neurology and
neuropsychology
it's all predicated on that idea so i
think it's deeply ingrained within
ourselves and within our science um
and uh you know within
uh
perception generally that consciousness
comes from outside
and you you're speaking about some
further um you know
ramifications of that and therefore
sources of resistance against the
alternative view but all the evidence
suggests that consciousness is
endogenous consciousness is generated
from within
um and
i mean you saw i i had i i i'm sorry i
don't know who the person was who made
the comment about you know how do we
know that this is not you know just some
sort of program spewing out language um
i have nothing against you i don't know
who you are
i just hear that all the time
and uh you know i i find that frankly i
find it astonishing you know that you
present all of this evidence and then
still people say well you know how do
you know but how do you know that that
these patients are really conscious and
this is a this this this demonstrates
the extent
of the
of the prejudice you know that has come
with that with that historical um with
that legacy
that
stephen with a raised hands then dave
with a raised hand we'll go with the
raised hands
okay thanks um yeah so sort of following
on from that yeah i totally agree and
actually i think the work with first
piston and active vision
um is is quite helpful because the idea
that we're reaching out and feeling the
world
and i think actually i was looking back
before 300 400 years ago
if you went back in time people actually
almost had that as a an intuition that
we were looking out in the world but
once we discovered the retina and then
photography we kind of re-imagined
um
so one question i've got is is regarding
cerebral palsy i work a lot with
communities with complex disability with
non-verbal
and their pre-motor cortex is often
damaged and in the 1970s it was thought
medically if you couldn't speak you
couldn't think so that was where they
were then if you couldn't communicate
words
and then once they started using symbols
bliss symbolics and the ability to
then and they suddenly discovered that
all these clients who had
who were non-verbal actually
perform complete sentences because they
have a way to act in the world and
interact in the world
and develop um language syntax and all
of that so i'm just thinking whether
you've had a lot of uh whether any of
this works been tied in with clients
with cerebral palsy
not only with cerebral palsy but with
all sorts of
neurological conditions
if i can just sort of piggyback on what
you've said about cerebral palsy
the whole trend
within clinical neurology
has been
us realizing that patients who we
thought were not conscious actually are
conscious
um
and the whole
the the sort of tenor of the research
that's been done
in recent decades um i mean locked in
syndrome of course is the extreme
example but but i don't only mean locked
in syndrome i mean all of these states
of reduced and obtunded uh con and
clouded consciousness and so on
minimally conscious states
so-called vegetative states and so on
we're finding more and more patients who
actually who we thought
were not conscious with increasing
technology we find that they are
um
with with improvements in our methods we
find that they are
so it's it's a sort of an odd um
it's an odd um contradiction with the
sorts of philosophical skepticism and
doubt that one confronts from people who
say well you know
you know how do we know they're
conscious
they're behaving as if they're conscious
but maybe they're not
in fact what we've been finding in
clinical neurology is patients who
behaving as if they're not conscious
and then when we
when we use the proper tools we find
that they actually are
so
um
your comment about
cerebral palsy can be multiplied you're
the observations that you refer to
consciousness um you know using
reportability
as a criterion
the capacity to declare
your conscious states
has really
it's not just led to
methodological and epistemological
problems it's really led to gross
clinical errors you know it's ethical
problems
i i feel we need a lot more than mere
philosophical skepticism
before we can take seriously in
neurology which after all is a branch of
medicine before we can take seriously
the possibility that these kids and
these patients look as if they conscious
behave as if they're conscious say that
they're conscious and we say well we
can't be sure i mean think about the
implications
thanks mark
dave with a question
yes um
two i'd like to say two things uh to
what you were just talking about uh the
difficulty of telling whether people who
seem to be locked in or comatose are
conscious
there have been some people who
initially got their experience in
working with the diet they just wanted
to people who were dying to not be alone
and they spent a lot of time as
typically as volunteers
sitting with folks who seem to be
comatose who seem to be completely
unresponsive
and they found that events that unroll
very very slowly
in the patient's room seemed to elicit a
response
and they got in high-speed cameras and
would
uh record
what the patient is doing that's a study
that's also been done with with infants
that infants seem to to act extremely
fast
uh and that if you speed up those
images you can actually see a child
responding who seems to be kind of lying
there they found with the comatose that
it seemed they can carry out
conversations and it actually did
resemble conversations taking a person
through childhood scenes
for instance and watching them respond
and they nod or they'd shake or they
grin you mentioned some kid that used to
bully you
over a period of minutes maybe saying it
over and over or speaking very slowly
and you get this very slow but
eventually a full grin that a nurse
would say oh that's just a grimace now
let me check her diaper
and the other thing is a much better
bigger picture question
who actually is hyper alert
getting out of professional settings or
ideological settings you walk around you
see someone who's just you got to be
really careful with and they will just
startle
you have to be really careful what
what you say you don't bring up
unpleasant topics you never imply that
they've done something wrong who are
these
for the most part
these hyper alert individuals are
children of alcoholics
who as small children had to be
the responsible person they had to keep
daddy from hurting mommy
even and i wonder how is niels bohr
raised
was he hyper alert is that why he became
so
amazingly oppressive as nice as he might
have been nonetheless
unremittingly insistent that only he was
correct
so in that big picture thing are the
folks who want to insist that you
absolutely positively are controlled
only from the outside were they the
child the people who as children were
never able to emit
they always had to react they always had
to be really really careful because the
environment really is something that
will come in and get you
well um about your second uh comment
i will just say
uh please note uh how affective uh you
know
all of this stuff is that you're talking
about and i i i think that
we we really
underestimate the importance of affect
in terms of the whole gamut of
phenomena that we
call consciousness
but to your first point i want to make
clear uh that
i am i mean i agree with what you're
saying uh
the about
the the
um
inference of consciousness in these
patients
uh but i but i want to make clear that
i'm making actually a quite a
in light of or
notwithstanding or you know all of this
other evidence and all of these other
very interesting uh clinical phenomena
all of which
uh point in the direction of we've
underestimated the presence of
consciousness you know that we've
we've been relying on a very
poor
criteria
in terms of reportability
and so on
that really we need more sophisticated
methods and the more we use more
sophisticated methods the more we find
evidence that there is in fact somebody
there
i agree with all of that but i'm making
a very
very limited claim
i'm saying i'm not saying these kids are
like you and me i'm not saying they have
a full rich inner mental life
i'm saying only that there is something
it is like to be them
um and in light of all the evidence in
their cases plus all the other evidence
that i've cited or using all these
different methods all i'm saying is that
that's something it is likeness that
these kids possess
is it feels like something they have
feelings that's all i'm saying so it's
it's all very interesting all these
other things about how all these other
capacities um have been missed by us in
relation to all of these other
neurological conditions but in these
cases which have no cortex whatsoever
they have only
some of them have basal ganglia and and
you know other subcortical for brand
nupi some of them don't
but even in cases you have no forebrain
only a brain stem
they
display
affects and so i'm saying that the brain
stem
prerequisite form of consciousness
does have a quality and the content
it therefore feels like something there
is something it is like to be these kids
and and that quality and content is
affected that's all i'm claiming that
the foundational form of consciousness
is affect and it's generated in the
brainstem
so
it's a it's a it's actually i think a
rather modest claim
in light of all the evidence it's quite
a conservative claim it's a sort of it's
a sort of a deflationary claim
but so much flows from just that
and i i'll just say once more
i find it very hard to understand i mean
i can understand
you know and of course or politically or
what you know i mean people's whole
careers i mean generations of careers
have been built on the assumption you
know that that that cortex and
consciousness um are are intrinsically
bound up with each other which you know
so the people have a hell of a lot to
lose and and many of us with egg on our
faces and i freely admit that i uh too
uh believed that the cortex was the
organ of consciousness this is what i
took in like mother's milk when i
trained
and i believed that for many many years
after i trained you know
so you know i'm not exempted from that
but gosh we've got to look at the
evidence it's wrong we made a mistake
you know it's not doesn't mean the
cortex does nothing it doesn't mean it
doesn't contribute anything to
consciousness it's just not the source
of consciousness the the cortex is
elaborates this very raw
primary elemental feeling that is
generated in the brain stem and all we
need to do is accept that and uh and
then we'll make huge progress in
consciousness science uh the the the the
fallacy that the cortex is the source of
consciousness uh is really a serious
impediment to us at this point uh in the
history of our field
i i think it's you next daniel
yes
it is indeed a theme of the discussion
that ambiguous evidence are continually
interpreted and reinterpreted in light
of our inherited or our previously
structured priors
and that's true in the active vision
example it's also true in the scientific
example
where our inherited priors about
scientific models influence how new
evidence is not just perceived but
funded and carried out
and um
[Music]
it made me think about uh when people
activate a gene or remove one gene and
make claims of function
might be an analogous to the brain but
removing or having one node in a complex
network
showing that there is a single point of
failure or
gain of function does not entail that as
a generating mechanism which is just an
example of an explanation that retains
an alternative perspective and so i
think it's
interesting on multiple levels as we
kind of apply this idea of updating and
learning and structural learning on our
theories
about ostensibly the part of the body
that does this function as opposed to
one's hand which is important and has
nerves in it but doesn't do this kind of
engagement
thanks very much um
so i agree that's an everyday
observation um that uh
you know we we are reluctant to accept
uh
prediction errors uh
we we we cling to our priors especially
our most deeply consolidated priors
and
we see this in everyday life nobody
likes to find they were wrong that they
have to change their mind that they have
to accept
evidence for review other than the one
that they
had always held and this applies even to
our scientists
i mean who uh in their graduate studies
when they were doing their first
research you know didn't hope uh that
their hypothesis was right uh and then
when the evidence came in and they found
oh dear you know i haven't found what i
expected to find it's not welcome
so what i'm referring to based on what
you've just said um i know this is not
quite what you were saying i'm sort of
elaborating what you were saying
um is that we don't recognize
uh sufficiently the affect of dimension
uh in our resistance um to prediction
errors you know we
we we we all know about you know friars
and posteriors and you know and how this
all works mechanistically but just from
the sort of anecdotes that i've
mentioned um
we
i'm i'm i'm i'm trying to get us to
recognize that there is an affective
dimension to that and when we get to
this point about the concentric
predictive hierarchy i'll come back to
that
but i think it's an it's an it's an
interesting and important observation
that as you
traverse the hierarchy um
and and get to what uh in my way of
thinking about it as a concentric
hierarchy to get deeper into the
hierarchy in the traditional way we
speak of going higher in the hierarchy
but as we go deeper further from the
sensory motor periphery
so
we come upon priors which are which are
more and more difficult
to update um and uh i say again there's
a there's a there's a feeling that goes
with that which is
i don't care what you tell me i'm not
gonna believe you
thank you mark stephen with a question
yeah i know you're going to come back to
the cognitive consciousness um but just
something around terminology we've been
doing work around an ontology working
group at the active inference lab
actually trying to understand how to
think about the language and
you mentioned it could be um
affects it is generated in the brainstem
and then
um
and that's when something's like
something
that's what it's like but i'm also
wondering how are you taking the dynamic
with the body and environment going down
i don't know if that's seen as another
manifestation
because obviously
it makes sense because it's it's more
integrated with the rest of the body's
nervous system it's less distant from it
but um i'm wondering whether the term
um generated within is is more to do
with when it's connected to the
rest of the brain and
when it goes down it's actually more
distributed in the mind body environment
dynamic
um
the
i would have nothing against i mean
that way of thinking
is um i'm very sympathetic with it
i'm i'm not a narrow localizationist
uh i'm i'm very um
very happy to recognize um it comes
naturally to me to think about
functional systems which are distributed
and dynamic
and
and and in fact
the the reticular activating system is
probably the most deeply interconnected
with everything else in the brain system
that there is
um it is it is
it has tentacles everywhere and not only
although it's called the ascending
reticular active agent system it
descends also you know it's uh
it modulates the whole nervous system
um in very important ways that that will
come to you know because this whole
thing of precision modulation um is at
the heart of my way of understanding
consciousness
um so
the the main thing that i'm wanting to
say is i agree with you uh that the the
the this is a deeply uh interconnected a
system
which functions uh by modulating other
systems
and
i would be very happy if it were
if we had to leave it there and say well
you can't quite say that affect is
generated in the reticular activating
system because you know it's it's really
modulating these other systems
my
reluctance however in this case
to accept that um is twofold
uh the one is that
that's the kind of thing that people
like joe ladue are saying they're saying
yeah this is all unconscious until it is
labeled by
or read out in
cortex
uh you're not talking about cortex uh so
you know that's but the principle
remains you know that this
i i i don't want to concede the point
that it only becomes conscious once it
modulates something else and that that's
really where the contents and qualities
are
that's a sort of theoretical reluctance
on my part you can see why
but more importantly and more tellingly
uh it is the evidence uh when you look
at these kids
they have no cortex so their efforts
can't be modulating
it can't be the result of something that
the brainstem is doing to cortex
because there ain't no cortex and yet
you know there's all the evidence that
they have affects um
and so i think uh as much as surprising
as it may be uh you know it's it's it's
not consistent with our normal way of
thinking about cortex and it's also not
something that i'm wedded to the idea
that that that you know anything is
generated in anything
but the evidence suggests that certainly
uh the modulatory influence that the
reticular activating system has over the
cortex true as it is important as it is
fundamental as it is to how that system
works
um
that the affects are not a product of
the modulation of cortex
the effects are generated in the
subcortical structures and if you just
take a step back and
the the implication of that
is that
well maybe there are affects
in vertebrates who don't have cortex in
other words maybe affects are not the
exclusive preserve of mammals um and
actually that seems pretty likely it
seems pretty darn likely
that
non-mammalian vertebrates have aspects
and again you know when you start
looking at the evidence it's pretty darn
good that they do
so um i i'm happy to accept everything
that you're saying about let us not
forget that this is a system which is
deeply interconnected with other systems
that its primary function is to modulate
other systems
but all i'm saying is that when it comes
to cortex
it's not that the affects themselves are
not generated by the modulating of
cortex that doesn't mean that there's a
disembodied brain
or disembodied reticular activating
system but you can have a decorticated
reticular activating system
and it can generate effects
nonetheless
thank you mark dave do you wanna thanks
go
okay so
one thought i see that the
the comments in the chat line have they
been dealt with can i move on
yes
let's try to get to at least one other
of these important points
oh well this is a brief point
um you know the reason i'm making this
point
um about affect not being synonymous
with with interceptive inference is
because those few people uh working
within the active inference framework
who are not corticocentric and happily
they are increasing you know there's
there's uh
people who worked within this framework
they had no reason to question you know
all of the mainstream assumptions of
cognitive neuroscience as far as as far
as
cortex is concerned um the the
the but
slowly um it's become apparent uh that
affect uh is is uh is an important topic
that we we're not only talking about
perception and action and cognition uh
you know we're talking also about
affective processes and and about
you know body regulating processes and
so on um in fact the whole of
self-organization uh
you know has to do
with the regulation of the of the own
body and you know the whole notion of
self-evidencing systems and so on you
know
so so this is happily slowly coming
uh
and increasingly coming uh
into the mainstream of
um the af people working within the
within the sort of active inference
framework
um but
the the the dominant view within that uh
school of thought
is that affect
is to the internal body uh what
perception is to the external world in
other words extraception uh
is uh it is a perceptual inference
regarding uh things going on outside of
me
and affect uh is perceptual inference
about things going on inside of me
um and that's you know
if that were so that would be nice and
simple um but i i don't see it that way
so uh and the the perhaps the
outstanding proponent of the view
that affect is intraceptive inference is
a neil seth
and he's just brought out a a really
very good book um
i have it right here
here it is
being you
um you know which which is predicated on
on on that view
so because it's because i agree with him
about so many things i i think that
it's easy for people to conflate our
views and to imagine that what i'm
saying is the same as what he's saying
on this score
so i want to make clear that
i'm not saying the same as what he's
saying on the score that why do i think
that affect is not
the same as perception uh it's but but
rather interceptive perception
um
well
first of all
because there are many interceptive
perceptual states which are not
effective
so you know you can
you can
perceive this the the your heart rate uh
the beating of your heart you can
perceive uh your
your respiration
rate or the or the the the the the
inspiring and expiring uh of air from
your lungs you can perceive gurgling uh
in your tummy which is an unequivocally
visceral
state
and all of these things you can perceive
them indifferently you can perceive them
without any affective valence
or quality at all
so if affect were synonymous with
interceptive inference then why are
these common and garden examples
of interception not effective
and then
secondly
if affects were intraceptive perception
how come so many affects are generated
by extraceptive events
where
there doesn't seem to be any clear
interceptive
driving force so for example pain
which is a fairly
simple example of an affect you know you
stick a pin in my finger it comes from
the outside and it penetrates the you
know the nociceptors in my extraceptive
[Music]
nervous system
and
i feel this intense affect called pain
so that's extraception and yet it's
effective um the same applies to
surprise you know due to fright you know
you get a you get a you get a you get a
shock um
well in fact electric shock is another
one but these are but i i mean just you
know fright something unexpected happens
outside of you and you startle
and there's a there's a there's an
affect that goes with that a particular
type of disgust is another one you
imbibe something um that tastes smells
bad and you wretch it up with this
terrible feeling of disgust
and then they're more
and they're not purely entirely
non-bodily affective states like
missing somebody you know missing your
brother
it's clearly affective
and there's nothing bodily about it
so
and nothing intercepted about it when i
say nothing bodily i mean particularly
you know it's not it's not about the
state of your intraceptive
visceral processes
so i'm saying there are interceptive
visceral processes which we perceive
which are not effective
and they are affective processes uh
affective states that we
experience which are not interreceptive
so i don't think that we can say that
affect is interceptive inference that
it's the same as external perception
except it's directed toward the state
the internal state of the own body
i think that it's something else
and i don't say this to be difficult
you know i'm
i'm actually
quite uh
concerned that those few of us within
the active inference framework who are
recognizing the importance of affect uh
can't agree on this point because uh you
know
they're few enough of us you know who
recognize the the importance of africa
so i'm i'm just wanting to make clear
why i think that it's not merely a kind
of mirror image reflection um of of
extraceptive uh uh inference and then i
want to add one last point which is that
when you read
i mean everything that i'm going to go
on to argue about why
extraceptive perception remember what i
said at the very beginning about
cortical vision having been the model
example of where we will find the neural
correlative consciousness which has led
us down this blind alley
and and got us got us into such uh such
a mess
that that
it has to do
largely as i'm going to argue later with
the fact that cortical processes and
perceptual processes are not
intrinsically conscious things you can
perceive
the world
through all your extraceptive modalities
vision included at the cortical level
too you can perceive the world without
perceiving it consciously in other words
extraceptive inference
perceptual inference is not an
intrinsically conscious process
there's nothing about extraceptive
inference or perceptual inference that
that requires consciousness to for us to
understand the mechanisms at work and so
if interceptive inference is just the
same thing applied to the interior of
the organism it suffers all the same
problems
that it's it's not clear
why it becomes conscious
um and i said that's going to be my last
point on the school but in fact i
realized there's one more that i want to
make which is that um the vast vast
vast majority of our intraceptive
processes are unconscious
um i mean even more so than our
extraceptive processes
most of our regulation of our visceral
bodily economy happens autonomically we
know nothing about it
so um it would be again a very curious
place to find uh the um this the
essential mechanism of of consciousness
and in this case of affect
if
the majority of the mechanisms of this
kind in fact do not operate consciously
and if it suffers the very same problems
as
our extraceptive um
using using vision as a as a model
example using any form of perception i
think
as a model example of consciousness is
to make a mistake because consciousness
is not an afferent process
consciousness is an endogenous process
it's something generated
not from within the guts
but from within the core of the brain
and uh
that that's where we're going next
so i'll stop there for any any uh
comments on that point before i move to
the next one
great presentation important
distinctions and points
so indeed we'll take a breath
and
i think we can head on to the next one
okay thanks
so now
um
i've told you in relation to the point
i've just made
i i think that
uh the hard problem
uh of consciousness
has arisen uh in large part
from the
uh
example that we've used of consciousness
starting with crick
who has to be credited with
bringing consciousness into
center stage uh so you know i'm not i'm
not bashing crick um and i also have
said already i think it's perfectly
reasonable that he started where he did
um you know it's clear why he started
with visual perception as his example
where we should look for the neural
correlate of visual consciousness
and then distinguish you know
unconscious vision from conscious vision
and then there we have it then we have
the neural corumat and then we can
generalize from there um i'm saying that
it turns out that was an unfortunate
place to start and it links with what i
was saying earlier that's also why i'm
saying
i don't want us to make the same mistake
just just just turning it inwards and
saying we're dealing with perceptual
processes
so let me let me say why all of this
casts new lights on the hard problem
um yeah so yes chalmers the person who
formulated the hard problem in the very
paper that he formulated it and he says
what makes the hard problem hard and
almost unique is that it goes beyond
problems about the performance of
functions
to see this note that even when we've
explained the performance of all the
cognitive and behavioral functions in
the vicinity of experience they may
still remain a further unanswered
question
why is the performance of these
functions accompanied by experience a
simple explanation of the functions
leaves this question open why doesn't
all this information processing go on in
the dark free of any inner field so this
is a
core
aspect of chalmers's hard problem he's
saying that our normal
way of going about doing cognitive
neuroscience
where we take a mental
phenomenon and we say okay uh you know
let's see uh you know
which part of the brain needs to be
damaged in order to
disrupt this
this mental uh state and then you know
let's start piecing together what the
what this part of the brain does and how
it works and uh
next thing we end up with a wonderfully
complicated map
of all of the mechanisms at work
in in this case
using
the standard example
visual perception
thomas's point is that you can do this
this is standard the standard approach
in cognitive neuroscience
but it doesn't tell you why there is
something it is like to see
so
you can you know the famous knowledge
argument with mary the visual
neuroscientist she knows everything that
there is to know about the functional
mechanisms of visual perception but she
knows nothing about what it's like to
see
in in the in the in the example that
jackson or the story as jackson told us
you know she's never seen color but you
know i i like to extend and simplify his
arguments and just say she was born
blind
she knows everything there is to know
about the functional mechanisms of
vision but she's never experienced
vision
and if one day
she's blessed with
the gift of sight she will learn
something utterly new about vision
namely what it is like to see what
redness is like what cleanness is like
and so on and this is their argument the
argument is
that
the normal uh
way we proceed in cognitive neuroscience
namely to dissect the function uh and in
this way to explain uh the mental thing
that we're trying to explain works very
well for all of these
mental functions but it doesn't work
very well it doesn't work at all for
consciousness
defined as
what it is like
to perform these functions
so
uh they're
claiming chalmers is
and nagel and others of that ilk
that somehow
the consciousness is in a different
realm uh from every other mental
function because you know when you when
you've explained all the functional
mechanisms
you still are left with this epistemic
gap
between that explanation of the function
and the qualitative experiential
phenomenal feel of seeing
and
so i'm saying that the problem is that
they're using perception
as an example perception is not an
intrinsically conscious function
and indeed cortical perception is not
intrinsically conscious
that it is demonstrably the case that
the cortex can perform uniquely cortical
perceptual
operations
like
actually recognizing color you can
recognize color unconsciously and you
can recognize faces unconsciously you
can read words unconsciously so
um if the cortex can do all of this
perceptual and cognitive gymnastics
without consciousness i think it's
perfectly reasonable to say well why
doesn't all this information processing
go on in the dark without any inner feel
because that kind of information
processing can go on in the dark without
any inner feel a perceptual inference is
not intrinsically conscious
so
this uh
statement of chalmers is this really
a strong statement where he says there
is no cognitive function such that we
can say in advance that explanation of
that function will automatically explain
experience this is this is what he says
on the basis of
everything that i've just told you
that
this is the this is this is where he's
led he's saying that they you that
explaining the function can never
explain experience
if that's the case we're in big trouble
because consciousness is somehow you
know going to have to be dealt with in a
different way from everything else in
science
but if you change that word cognitive to
affective
um traumas
would charmers have said this there is
no affective function such that we can
say in advance that explanation of that
function will automatically explain
experience
i'm saying of course there is
the function of feeling
i am saying in advance
that explanation of the function of
feeling will automatically explain why
it feels like something because that is
the function of feeling the function of
feeling is for the organism to feel it
that to feel its own state
so i'm saying had we begun there had we
begun our quest uh for
the neural correlate of consciousness
with this model example had we had we
begun by asking
why
and how does it come about
that
feelings are experienced i think that we
would have had a much less hard time
with it than
we have had
with starting with with visual
information processing the mechanism of
vision
the mechanism even of cortical vision is
not intrinsically conscious it does not
automatically explain experience because
it does not automatically have to be
experienced but the mechanism of feeling
you cannot explain
how feeling works why feeling exists
what it's there for if you have a
functional account of feeling it would
have to account for why it feels like
something in other words why it's
experienced so i think that
what i said in my earlier point that um
that um
yeah
that these facts uh uh cast new light on
the hard problem uh the this is the new
light that
that it casts i just have also uh on the
screen this slide
this famous review paper by killstrom
which summarizes all the experimental
evidence
for
the conclusion that we were led to
actually a good four decades ago already
that perception without awareness of
what is perceived is perfectly
commonplace and learning without
awareness of what is learnt is perfectly
cognitive and perceptual functions
performed by the cortex are not
intrinsically conscious processes so
this question of chalmers is why is the
performance of these functions
accompanied by experience why doesn't
all this information processing go on in
the dark that perplexity is not
difficult to understand
in light of
those facts
but i don't think that this question has
anything like the same
gravity
uh when you apply it to
the kinds of mechanisms that give rise
to feeling i'm saying in short that if
mary was an affective neuroscientist
rather than a cognitive neuroscientist
or a visual neuroscientist
she could not know everything that there
is to know about the functional
mechanisms
underpinning feeling without
expecting that it will generate
something that is experienced
without
without the mechanism necessarily
accounting for why it is experienced and
this is why i think at shifting our
focus from cortex to brain stem and from
perception to affect um has big
implications for
our
ability to
finally come to grips with this hard
problem of consciousness
i'll pause there again thank you
thank you mark i'll read a comment in
the chat and then you can respond then
stephen so
dean writes
pre-arousal plus awareness minimum of
two
not as brain geography or territory
establishment effort rather
a dance
in an evolving relationship as we might
see in an agent dancing with the
environment whereas the territorial view
might examine control
brain stem of the cortex or vice versa
one in an in controlling relationship
through a mechanical lens
this relationship of arousal and
awareness could be choreographed but not
choreographed mechanized but not
necessarily choreographed
not sure what that part meant our
feelings a residue of arousal plus
awareness revealed
we accept the signals like we dance out
a path
generated
look i think that this is similar to the
point that we were discussing earlier
you know about um generated in uh you
know the upper brain stem as opposed to
the upper brain stem modulating other
other other structures
whether they be
above or below the brain stem in the
nervous system
i said then i'm very happy to think of
it as a dance uh as something
choreographed where it's not a matter of
whose master and whose servant you know
um that that's a is it's a
when it comes to the relationship
between the affective arousal um and and
cortical
representation i think that there's some
instances where
affective arousal just absolutely um
brushes aside any amount of uh decision
making and thought processing and
conversely uh the opposite happens too
you know that there clearly are ways in
which where one can
in a top-down way modulate affect
dramatically
and i don't only mean you know regulate
your emotions i mean if you look at some
of these examples of these buddhist
monks who are able to you know really
massively control
autonomic functions and and the affects
that normally would go you know with uh
not breathing or walking on uh you know
painful um
surfaces and so on that those affects
seem to be overridden so
i have nothing against the idea of there
being a choreography
between
brain stem and cortex
but
i've already said why i think
that in this instance the affects do not
require the cortex
to be
actually qualify for the name affect
that they actually are felt without
cortex i've already said why
what the evidence is
both in terms of
studies
of uranus studies using the various
methods that i mentioned
the most dramatic being as i said cases
where there is no cortex and yet there's
evidence that
there's there's plenty
of affect there
but also the evolutionary implications
of that which is that we don't have to
wait for the appearance of cortex
and the mammalian series for uh that for
the for the dawn of consciousness that
if if if affect is generated in the
subcortical structures uh then um affect
uh it does not require cortex and affect
is a it can be um
can be uh
attributed
to
other vertebrates and not only
vertebrates by the way there also is
good evidence that
some invertebrates
are conscious
of the octopus is the famous the most
famous example
um but i think that there's a further
problem in this comment you know which
has to do with the word awareness um you
know you speak of arousal and awareness
and you seem to attribute arousal to
particular activating system which i'm
happy with
and awareness to cortex which i'm not so
happy with if
if if you mean that
you cannot be aware of arousal
without cortex so i think this word
awareness it's like all the other words
i mentioned at the beginning like
emotion and affection and i said i want
to i want to use the word feeling to
make clear what i'm talking about
because these words mean different
things to different people the word
awareness means different things to
different people and to to many people
it seems to mean something like
reflective awareness
in other words you know
in other words being aware of what
you're aware of
or access consciousness
as ned block calls it you know that
there's this sort of phenomenal
consciousness which is some kind of like
a raw consciousness and then there's a
then there's a subject that that
accesses
this information it's it's like the
global workspace theory works that i
mean it's pretty similar sort of idea
um if if we're going to reserve the word
awareness for that higher order thought
or reflective consciousness or access
consciousness
then it means that we can't attribute um
awareness to raw fields
uh and um
you know
that's that's an odd use of the word
awareness to me um to me how can you
feel pain
without being aware of it you know and
um
and pain
um you don't need to have any kind of
reflective cognition about it you don't
need to have any explanatory labeling uh
or anything it's just like that's
so and you pull away even if you don't
have language even if you're not human
even if you're not a mammal
even if you're another kind of creature
so um i
arousal for me implies uh awareness um
in the way i use the word but um if if
we're going to use awareness for
that higher order type of consciousness
then i would just want to remind you
that there are other types of
consciousness
that don't possess that kind of
awareness
which nevertheless have something it is
likeness um and and the core of that
quality is feeling
that something it is like this is
feeling
thank you mark stephen
yes thank you um
so i was wondering if we think of um
consciousness as a kind of an
integration of our accent action
expectations of what's happening
and
those expectations then were
and casper hesp talks about this with
his work with active imprints but
is how
those expectations were weren't met can
be effective
um so i was wondering within that kind
of that prediction process um
when someone
gets a question right so you have a
mathematician when they get it right
they get a feeling that it's right it's
like it's a felt sense
and you could ask someone what's that
feeling like and they can sort of bring
out a metaphor landscape
that relates to that like it can
actually have a structure
and there's a similar thing with pain as
well pain
has to be expressed as a metaphor you
have to say it's like a stabbing or it's
a
throbbing or it's a it's always some
kind of
dynamical kind of metaphorical
embodiment
so i'm just curious um
has these you know this embodiment this
meeting
in this brainstem uh how you
how you how you see that in terms of if
that's congruent with you and
whether this this is then uh sort of a
re-reimagining
consciousness is like a reimagining of
these
of these expectations
um and it can
it could go up or down
in terms of how that
is being kind of
realized
so i'd like to separate out two
different aspects of what you're saying
um
the the first has to do with metaphor
and um
i think that
that
may be true
of um
of
being able to report or declare your
conscious states in language uh that
somehow or other you have to symbolize
because language is is just that
it's a symbolic
representation
of the
thing itself
um
so
that as long as you you you use the word
expressing it
yes you can't express
in words
and emotion without using some sort of
metaphor
some sort of symbolic system in order to
be able to communicate it to others
they can of course be the direct
behavioral effect of display expression
of the emotions in darwin's sense of the
use of that term uh that which we then
um
us symbolic species um you know we
we we use that symbolically uh too
but um i i don't think that the raw
feeling itself has to be
re-represented in any way i think it can
just be
the raw feeling um without it being
represented
in in in any language in the broader
sense of the word
and so i don't think that metaphor
is
a necessary component of the core
feature
of feeling
then the other thing you were saying
which had to do with
uh with surprise uh uh if i understood
you correctly
um i i i i
at times in my own thinking about this
there were times when i was keen on
thinking about
affect or linking affect more with error
signals than with
than with inferences themselves um the
and that was you know
i was thinking along those lines because
so many people within the active
inference framework
were speaking
about perception you know this famous
phrase controlled hallucination that
perception is fantasy
that it is the it is the upshot of the
predictive process
um and uh what worried me about that is
the very thing i've been banging on
about all along you know which is that
perception is not
intrinsically conscious and so this
business of inferring
the source
of your sensory signals
doesn't explain why there's something it
is like to infer the the source uh uh
of your or
the cause uh of your of your
sensory signals and so so so from that
sort of point of view um i've i found
myself thinking well it it's not so much
that you know i mean imagine if what you
perceive is just what you predict that
that that would be you know bloody
dangerous um so the controlled aspect
seemed to me to be the more important
aspect it's the it's the constraint on
what you predict um that seems to be
more the upshot of what we call
perception as as opposed to
hallucination and so i i wanted to place
the emphasis
um more
uh on
on the error side of things
than on the than on the prediction side
of things
um
but subsequently i i have changed my
mind uh on on that score um
[Music]
for which will become clearer you know
when i when i get down here where is it
uh when i get down here um which we're
obviously not going to get to today uh
but i'm i'm very much looking forward to
us having a second meeting where we can
get there for me uh it's it's got
everything to do
with the
uh with the modulation of confidence in
the prediction uh versus uh the area
signal or the error signal that is that
that is connected with uh that
particular prediction um and and i will
just say it now because we're not going
to get to it in this meeting um that
that the pithy formulation
of the way that i see it
is that it is good
when things turn out as expected and it
is bad when uncertainty prevails and i
mean here goodness and badness um in as
in the in the evaluative sense of the
word that is linked to the primary um
value system of all living things you
know which is that it is bad to die and
it is good to survive and if things are
turning out as expected in other words
you have a prediction
which actually
cuts it
that that is good
from the viewpoint of the organism um
and that if things are not turning out
as expected and uncertainty is uh
prevailing that is bad uh
it means you know this this is likely to
end in tears
and so um
the
the the
the uh
what was it the choreography that
somebody with the dance that somebody
else was talking about earlier and i
think that what
that that the the crucial thing here
is the is the is the palpating of the
precision uh the modulating of the
precision uh in the predictions uh uh
over the error signals uh and that that
is at the heart of what affects all
about and i'm only saying that now uh in
advance because i know we're not going
to get there in in this meeting because
we've only got seven minutes to go
but i'm going to try if i may just
unless there any further questions and
comments are there any further questions
and comments
no here are some future comments it
takes many oh they are so then if
they're hostile something
i think what we should do is i'll take
i'll take whatever comments remain or
questions and then we'll start next time
with this point because i don't think i
can squeeze it in
to i don't think i should even try to
squeeze it into to too short at a time
period so
totally agree
yeah that was my comment was uh we will
have a last few minutes
to
really just appreciate you coming on for
the 16.1 and we'll find the time to do
16.2 when we will condense and sort of
reflect on what has already transpired
and look forward to these next
points i think it was really
great
to walk through it this way
so
stephen or dave do you have any last
thoughts otherwise mark
please have a last thought
so dave first then optionally stephen
and then mark
yeah in addition to professor seth whose
book we already have who else can we uh
check with as people doing ai without
the um
the
the constriction
with without which you mean with you
mean who else is working on affective
processes within within this
exam
[Music]
so
um two people who come to mind
immediately
is manos sakiris
they
both great
and uh
and also both of them are very good
speakers uh so so if you if you're
wanting to invite them on to uh this
this um
seminar
what live stream series i i think that
they would be
um they would do well
awesome thank you very much stephen
yeah just to say thanks very much and um
yeah we've
been reading some of the work of ryan
smith and casper hesp so oh well ryan
smith also
orion and and maxwell ramstead
they're also working on affect they both
are they i should have mentioned them
ryan smith and and maxwell ramstead
sorry
that they're doing some fabulous work i
really loved their recent paper on folk
psychology uh it was just brilliant
excellent oh thanks well we'll we'll be
connecting those dots up i'm sure next
time as well thank you
okay
well um thoughts yes mark yeah just just
to say that i appreciate having the um
i mean it's not every day that you have
two hours uh with with with excellent
minds uh to be able to talk about only
half of what you wanted to talk about so
it's been very kind of you uh to
um to um
give me this this this latitude uh and i
think that these issues
and i'm also particularly pleased that
you're going to be in one way or another
uh
recording and i don't just mean video
recording but also turning into some
sort of written form uh what we're
talking about because as i hope you can
see from what i've said just in half
of what i wanted to go through is really
are pretty
basic issues for for consciousness
science and for the science of the mind
and for
and
and by implication uh for what we can do
within this active inference framework
in tackling these
really i don't mean to be hyperbolic
when i say these profound and ancient
problems i think that we have real
prospects of being able to make
significant progress um on on these
fronts and so it deserves is the point
i'm making it deserves the time that
that we are giving it and i'm grateful
to you for um for recognizing that
well sir thank you very much thanks
thanks very much
thank you thank you